Guide to the John Zuccotti Papers 1956-2015 MS 3018
New-York Historical Society
John Zuccotti papers
1956-2015
New-York Historical Society
Zuccotti, John E.
MS 3018
564
15.08 Linear feet in 15 document boxes and one oversize flat box
The collection includes documents reflecting the range of John Zuccotti's (1937-2015) career in public service and in private practice as a lawyer and in real estate property development. The collection includes documentation concerning the Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG) of the early 1960s, initiatives of the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) in the late 1960s, the New York City fiscal crisis of the 1970s, a range of advisory committees and boards that Zuccotti chaired or otherwise participated in, and the dilemma posed in 2011 by the encampment of the Occupy Wall Street protestors in Zuccotti Park. Major themes throughout the collection are land tenure, land use, zoning, urban development, planning, housing, and economic development. New York City, especially lower Manhattan, is the context for much of the collection.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series I. Biographical and Photograph Files, 1960-2015
Series II. Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG) Project Files, 1956-1966, 1978
Series III. Housing & Urban Development (HUD) Files, 1966-1969
Series IV. Mayor's Advisory Committee on Police Management and Personnel Policy, 1983-1997
Series V. Speeches and Other Presentations, 1967-2015
Series VI. General Subjects, 1966-2013
Biographical/Historical Note
John Eugene Zuccotti was born 23 June 1937 in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of New York City, the son of Angelo and Gemma Zuccotti. He graduated from La Salle Military Academy and in 1959 received his B.A. in History from Princeton University. After Princeton, he fulfilled his military commitment by going to training for the Army Reserve, becoming a second lieutenant; he remained a reserve until 1967. After completing military training, Zuccotti attended Yale University Law School, earning his law degree in 1963. While a law student during the summer of 1962, Zuccotti interned in Washington, D.C., for Jacob K. Javits, the U.S. senator from New York. 1962 was a senatorial election year in New York, and Zuccotti was exposed to Javits's campaign activities. The politically liberal Javits would win re-election on the Republican Party ticket that November.
After graduating from Yale Law in the spring of 1963, Zuccotti accepted a temporary position with the Joint Center for Urban Studies of MIT and Harvard. At the time, the Joint Center was providing technical advice to the Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG), a Venezuelan public agency created in 1960 to design and implement a regional development program. Zuccotti moved to Venezuela to participate in the project from July 1963 to late 1964 or early 1965. (See Series II for further information about the CVG and the project.) In the summer of 1963, Zuccotti married Susan Sessions. The couple lived in Venezuela until Zuccotti's time with the project ended, at which time the Zuccottis returned to New York where John took up employment in early 1965 with the law firm Davis, Polk, Wardwell, Sunderland, & Kiendl.
About two years later, in late 1966, Zuccotti left Davis, Polk to move to Washington, D.C., where he worked as Special Assistant to Robert C. Wood (1923-2005), Undersecretary of the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). HUD was still in its infancy as a cabinet level department, having been formed in January 1966 out of a predecessor agency, the House and Home Financing Agency, as a result of Great Society legislation signed by President Lyndon B. Johnson in 1965. Wood had joined HHFA/HUD in 1965 from MIT where he had been a political scientist; he had been involved with the Joint Center and its Venezuelan project and he and Zuccotti knew each other from that connection. Zuccotti remained at HUD until January 1969 when he, along with Wood, left because of the change of presidential administrations from Johnson to Richard M. Nixon. Zuccotti stayed in Washington for another year, working as Secretary and Counsel to the National Corporation for Housing Partnerships.
In early 1970, Zuccotti returned to New York to become a founding partner with Peter Tufo and Joseph Johnston of the law firm Tufo, Johnston and Zuccotti. He and his wife moved to the Carroll Gardens section of Brooklyn, where they lived the rest of his life, raising three children. Zuccotti also began to take positions on Boards of Directors, including that of Material Systems Corporation, a company engaged in developing factory made low cost housing. In January 1971, a position that was required to be filled by a Brooklyn resident opened on the City Planning Commission; Mayor John V. Lindsay appointed Zuccotti to the spot. Two years later, in February 1973, Lindsay promoted Zuccotti to Chairman of the Planning Commission, at which point Zuccotti left his private law practice. Later in 1973, Mayor-elect Abraham Beame, a Democrat, re-appointed Zuccotti as Chairman. This chain of events was emblematic of the direction Zuccotti's career would follow in the coming decades: an expertise in urban planning, housing, land use, and zoning law that would put him at the center of private real estate development initiatives; political connections that kept him involved in some capacity in public service, but of a non-partisan quality that enabled him to support and be called on by both Democratic and Republican officials; and a highly competent "honest broker" who could navigate contentious public issues.
New York City faced severe fiscal difficulties during the Beame administration of the mid-1970s, with the city nearly declaring bankruptcy in 1975. One fallout of the negotiations to rescue the city financially was Mayor Beame's firing of his chief aide, First Deputy Mayor James Cavanagh. To replace him, Beame named Zuccotti to the position in December 1975. Zuccotti served in the position until June 1977, leaving a few months before Beame's defeat for re-election that November, and he is credited for being one of the stabilizing forces that contributed to New York's eventual economic recovery.
After leaving the Beame administration, Zuccotti returned to his private law practice and to the firm then named Tufo & Zuccotti where he represented various real estate development and other land use interests. In 1986, the firm merged with Brown, Wood, Ivey, Mitchell & Petty, with the combined law firm named Brown & Wood. In the late 1980s, one of Zuccotti's clients, the international real estate developer Paul Reichmann, approached him to take over management of Reichmann's commercial property development company, Olympia & York. At the time, Reichmann was intensely involved with developing the Canary Wharf project in London and sought an experienced hand to run O&Y's other properties, which included the World Financial Center, located next to the World Trade Center in lower Manhattan. Zuccotti accepted the offer and became President and Chief Executive Officer of Olympia & York in January 1990.
It soon became apparent that Reichmann had financially over-extended both himself and O&Y with the Canary Wharf project. He resigned from the company in early 1992 and Zuccotti was left to manage O&Y's financial crisis. After years of negotiation with O&Y's creditors and declaring bankruptcy as a strategic maneuver, Zuccotti successfully led the organization to recovery. In 1996, O&Y emerged from bankruptcy under a new name, World Financial Properties LP, with Zuccotti remaining as Chairman of the reorganized company. In February 1999, the company changed its name to Brookfield Financial Properties LP, which remains its name. Zuccotti held a leadership position in the Brookfield organization for the rest of his life. He died in 2015 of a heart attack at age 78.
The reorganization of Olympia & York in 1996 resulted initially in a much diminished company as a multitude of its properties were divested in order to satisfy creditors. Nevertheless, the new company that became Brookfield still held some important properties including those in Manhattan's Financial District, including two next to the World Trade Center complex. Consequently, Brookfield and Zuccotti were significant contributors to the recovery and rebuilding planning after the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001. One of Brookfield's properties damaged on 9/11 was Liberty Plaza Park, a privately-owned public space spanning one square block adjacent to the World Trade Center. After the park was renovated and re-opened in 2006 by Brookfield, it was renamed Zuccotti Park in honor of Brookfield's Chairman. The small plaza became famous in September 2011 when protestors against social and economic inequality chose Zuccotti Park as their site to place an encampment and launch the Occupy Wall Street movement. Given the private/public legal status of the plaza, and other considerations, there was a level of uncertainty on the part of the authorities as to how to deal with the occupation. After two months, in November the police raided the encampment and ended the Zuccotti Park occupation.
While the above sketches out the main thread of Zuccotti's career, through the 1980s and afterward, he was also involved in numerous other initiatives and positions. In 1982, he was appointed Impartial Arbitrator by the Metropolitan Transportation Authority and locals of the Transport Worker Union and Amalgamated Transit Union, a role he served for nine years. Zuccotti was Chairman of Mayor Edward I. Koch's Advisory Committee on Police Management and Personnel Policy (see series III) in 1985-87, a member of Koch's Advisory Task Force on the Homeless (1986-87), Chairman of Governor Hugh Carey's World Trade Center Task Force (1980-81) and a member of Carey's Economic Development Advisory Council with Felix Rohatyn and others (1979), and a member of Mayor David Dinkins's Managerial Review Commission (1991) and Commission on the Homeless (1991-92). He served over time on many corporate, non-profit and educational boards, including Co-Chair of the Citizens Commission on AIDS for New York City and Northern New Jersey (1987-91), Chairman of the Downtown Lower Manhattan Association, Chairman of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation, and trustee of Columbia University, to note a few. Zuccotti was a frequent speaker and panelist (such as his leadership of a workshop at the Regional Mobility Conference in 1988), and he was an adjunct professor at Yale Law in 1986-1988 and at Columbia Law for several terms in the 1990s.
(The above note was based on various on-line newspaper articles and from documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Susan Zuccotti, April 2016.
Scope and Contents Note
The collection includes documents reflecting the range of John Zuccotti's career in public service and in private practice as a lawyer and in real estate property development. The collection includes documentation concerning the Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG) of the early 1960s, the initiatives of the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) in the late 1960s, the New York City fiscal crisis of the 1970s, a range of advisory committees and boards that Zuccotti chaired or otherwise participated in, and the dilemma posed in 2011 by the encampment of the Occupy Wall Street protestors in Zuccotti Park, the small plaza in lower Manhattan named for him. Major themes throughout the collection are land tenure, land use, zoning, urban development, housing, and economic development. New York City, and especially lower Manhattan, is the context for much of the collection, though various HUD projects across the U.S. and the Venezuelan government's efforts in the Guayana region of Venezuela figure significantly in the documents. The collection includes speeches and other public remarks, correspondence, memos, published reports, unpublished papers, working files, clippings, some photographs, and other documents.
City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Ciudad Guayana (Venezuela); Economic development -- New York (State) -- New York.; Economic development -- Venezuela -- Guayana Region.; Employee-management relations in government -- New York (State) -- New York.; Financial crises -- New York (State) -- New York.; Letters (correspondence); Occupy movement -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.; Police administration -- New York (State) -- New York.; Real estate lawyers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Reports.; Speeches, addresses, etc.; Urban policy -- United States; Corporación Venezolana de Guayana; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986; Joint Center for Urban Studies; New York (N.Y.). Mayor's Advisory Committee on Police Management and Personnel Policy.; United States. Department of Housing and Urban Development; Wood, Robert Coldwell, 1923-2005; Zuccotti, John E.
- Series I. Biographical and Photograph Files, 1960-2015; 230166; 2.63 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series includes documents from John Zuccotti's early life and career and those that provide a general biographical perspective. The series includes biographical sketches written about Zuccotti from the 1970s to 2014, awards and other recognitions he received, photographs of him, especially from the 1970s, and newspaper and magazine clippings.
  Zuccotti's months in 1962 as an intern for U.S. senator Jacob Javits are reflected in the series with Javits position papers, re-election campaign materials and a photograph of Zuccotti with the senator and other interns. Other New York Republican campaign material from this period is also in the series. Zuccotti's student years at Yale Law School are documented with moot court material, his review of Jane Jacobs's The Death and Life of Great American Cities, and other documents.
  The series holds several folders of correspondence, including some relating to his years as Chair of the City Planning Commission and as Deputy Mayor. Much of the correspondence in the series includes congratulations on one of Zuccotti's career moves and expressions of thanks for donations, speaking appearances, or other matters.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is organized roughly by document type and subject matter.
  - Biographical Sketches, 1970-2014; 230175 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes biographical notes used over the course of the 1970s to 2014 for Zuccotti, and some resumes, applications, and other related material.
  - Memberships, 1973-1975; 230178 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes documents related to Zuccotti, then Chairman of the City Planning Commission, becoming a trustee of the City Club of New York (1973) and of the non-profit Suburban Action (1975). Also includes a provisional confirmation from Long Island University of Zuccotti's appointment to an adjunct professor position in Urban Studies (1975).
  - Awards & Recognition (Folder 1 of 6), 1982-1984; 230187 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes Best of New York Award (1982) program; Ubi Caritas Award from Catholic Charities of the Diocese of Brooklyn (1984) program and Zuccotti's draft remarks; Certificate of Appreciation from Brooklyn Bridge Centennial Commission (1983-84); and American Jewish Congress Man of the Year (1984) program, photograph, remarks by Mayor Edward I. Koch, and other documents.
  - Awards & Recognition (Folder 2 of 6), 1982-1983; 230188 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes Yeshiva University's Cardozo School of Law's Distinguished Public Service Award (1983) program, publicity, and contact sheets and other photographs of Zuccotti in his office for consideration for use in publicity.
  - Awards & Recognition (Folder 3 of 6), 1990, 1999; 230189 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes the Brooklyn Democrats Annual Award (1990) program and Eye-Bank's Man of Vision (1999) article in its newsletter.
  - Awards & Recognition (Folder 4 of 6), 2001; 230190 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes recipient of honor from Brooklyn Borough President Howard Golden as part of ceremony honoring achievements of Italian-Americans; news release and photographs.
  - Awards & Recognition (Folder 5 of 6), 2008; 230191 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes a DVD with tribute video to Zuccotti presented at the Notes of Hope Dinner at the National September 11 Memorial & Museum at the World Trade Center. Digital item is currently restricted.
  - Awards & Recognition (Folder 6 of 6), 2010, 2014; 230192 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes farewell presentation to Zuccotti as he left the Board of Wellpoint, Inc. (2010) and Leadership Award from the New York Building Congress (2014) program and seating chart.
  - Yale Law School (2 folders), 1960-1963; 230255 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-10)
    Includes Zuccotti's certificate of initiation into the international legal fraternity of Phi Delta Phi; two invitations from the Lep and Lace Society for cocktails at the Fence Club; rules for the Yale Moot Court of Appeals (1960); Zuccotti's brief for respondent in the 1961 Moot Court of Appeals; 1961 Fall Term exam for Property II; the text of a lecture by Professor P.E. Nedbailo titled "Political Organization of the Society of the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic in Our Time"; a carbon copy of Zuccotti's "Dead or Alive: A Review of The Death and Life of Great American Cities by Jane Jacobs," written for the Saturday Review in connection with the Law & Public Opinion course (1962); and notes on mortgages.
  - Foreign Area Fellowship Program Study Proposal, 1962 November; 230277 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes Zuccotti's grant proposal to study housing policy in Latin America.
  - Internship with U.S. Senator Jacob K. Javits (R-NY), [1962]; 230541 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes a portrait photograph of Javits and a photograph of Zuccotti and other interns with Javits and related press releases.
  - Javits. Congressional Record Remarks, 1961-1962; 230545 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes tear sheets from the Record of various Javits remarks, with related drafts.
  - Javits. Position Papers, 1962?; 230546 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes Javits position paper against Communism and his related voting record for 1957-61, and a position paper on business and the economy. Also includes a promotional brochure "Sen. Jacob K. Javits Welcomes You to Your Nation's Capital."
  - Javits. Re-election Campaign Speakers Kit (3 folders), 1962; 230549 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15-17)
    Includes a complete kit with brochures, statement of acceptance of renomination, policy statement on Cuba, a "model Speech" on Javits, and several fact sheets on his various policy positions.
  - Javits. Other Re-Election Campaign Material, 1962; 230554 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes two brochures, stationery, and three addresses: "Why I Am a Republican" (delivered at Fordham and NYU); "Health, Education, and the National Interest" (delivered at University of Buffalo); and "The American Economy" (delivered at a luncheon of Long Island business, labor and civic leaders, and at Hofstra).
  - Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller Legislative Accomplishments, 1962; 230559 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes various documents related to Rockefeller's achievements as governor, likely produced mostly in connection with his 1962 re-election campaign. Among the documents are "The Four Year Record of Republican Accomplishments: A Preliminary Report," "The Rockefeller Republican Record," "New York State - New York City: Fiscal Relations," "New York City Finances," Rockefeller's remarks at the opening of the Republican campaign headquarters at Hotel Roosevelt in New York City, an admission ticket and dinner invitation for the election night events at headquarters, and an outline of material for use by John Wells in a speech before the Women's Professional Club. A Javits campaign lapel button is attached to one of the documents.
  - John V. Lindsay Election Campaign Materials, 1965; 230563 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes two Lindsay for Mayor bumper stickers, a handbill, and a pamphlet "The Myth of Beame's Record."
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 1960-2005; 230566 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes various documents including a test booklet from Zuccotti's coursework in Economics 308 at Princeton; a clipping announcing Zuccotti's engagement to Susan Sessions; a NAACP membership card (1964); membership cards for the Yale Co-Operative Corp; a bank statement dating from Zuccotti's time at Fort Sill, Oklahoma (June 1960); a menu from a Zuccotti event held at Ristorante Il Cortile on Mulberry Street, autographed by proprietor(?) Antonio Morello; a Missionaries of St. Charles card holder with prayer cards and medallion (1987); name badge from Olympia & York; invitation and program for the inauguration of U.S. President George W. Bush (2005); a statement "John J. [Jack] Gilhooley: Republican Candidate for City Comptroller" (circa 1962); and a few other documents.
  - Photographs. Stock Portraits (7 folders), circa 1973-1977; 231279 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22-28)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes various headshots of Zuccotti, likely dating from his tenure as Chair of the City Planning Commission and/or Deputy Mayor. Images include Zuccotti speaking, speaking on the phone, and at his desk. There are several copies of many of the images. Prints are 5x7 inches and 8x10 inches, all black-and-white. There are some negatives of the prints.
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, circa 1971-1974; 231328 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
    Includes photographs dated or identifiable to Zuccotti's years on the City Planning Commission. Includes his swearing-in by Mayor John V. Lindsay; Zuccotti, Lindsay and other Commission members presenting a Community Planning Handbook; a Commission group portrait; and a press conference with President Giovanni Leone of Italy.
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1975; 231329 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes Zuccotti with Ralph Nader and others, and an unidentified event involving a mayoral proclamation.
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1976; 231330 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
    Includes a photo of Zuccotti being sworn in as Deputy Mayor by Mayor Abraham Beame (inscribed by Beame) and a photo with Zuccotti's family at the event; an event labeled "Italians from Genoa in April"; and with music awards honorees.
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1977; 231331 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
    Includes snapshots taken at a ceremony in Battery Park in honor of Verrazzano; with Supreme Court Justice Thurgood Marshall; and at Mayor Beame's State of the City address.
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1979; 231332 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
    Includes a photograph of Zuccotti at a black tie event shaking hands with U.S. President Jimmy Carter. Abe Beame and others also in the photo.
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1970s; 231333 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
    Includes various unidentified and/or undated photographs, though they all appear to date from the 1970s. A few include references: one refers to a "salute to Carnegie Hall" and "Happy Birthday to Isaac Stern"; another is inscribed from "Mary"; and one is a snapshot taken at an Inner Circle event.
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1980-1985; 231337 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
    Includes Zuccotti with Jack Bigel at a United Cerebral Palsy of Queens award event for Bigel (1980); Zuccotti and other Real Estate Division members on a UJA-Federation Mission to Israel (1981); and at the Port Authority's Harbor Festival dinner (1985).
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1992-1996; 231338 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)